Guide to the Roger McNiven Papers MC.198
New York University Archives
Roger McNiven Papers
1973-1988
New York University Archives
McNiven, Roger, 1943-1988
MC.198
3 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box
Roger McNiven was a Cinema Studies instructor and doctoral candidate at the Tisch School of Arts at New York University. He later went on to work at various film festivals and American universities as a professor. This collection contains notes, papers, and research conducted by Roger McNiven when he was a graduate student in the Cinema Studies program at New York University. It also contains paperwork and course materials from courses he taught at several colleges, papers from his time as the Director of the Movie Museum in Massachusetts, as well as several obituaries for McNiven.
Related Archival Materials
Records of the Office of the Dean of the Tisch School of the Arts, 1956-1981 (RG 35)
Arrangement
Files are arranged in chronological order within each series. This collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Coursework
Series II: Professional Acitivities
Series III: Employment
Series IV: Obituaries
Access Restrictions
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Box 1 and portions of boxes 2 and 3 are restricted due to FERPA regulations.
Biography of Roger McNiven
Roger David McNiven was born on September 17, 1943, in Australia. He received a Bachelor of Arts from the University of Queensland in Brisbane, Australia in 1980 and a Master of Arts degree in cinema studies from New York University in 1983. He published widely in academic journals for cinema studies, and served as an adjunct professor teaching cinema history and theory at New York University, Iona College, Saint Francis College, and Concordia University. He was the director of the first and second annual Spoleto Film Festival in Charleston, South Carolina from 1977-1978. In his time spent in New York he created two film showing societies; the Thousand Eyes Cinema which is since merged with the Bleecker Street Theater from 1973-1974, and the Cineclub from 1972-1977. In 1987, he developed The Reach Film Festival in Key West Florida. At the time of his death, he was completing his doctoral dissertation at New York University at the Tisch School of Arts.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains notes, papers, and research conducted by Roger McNiven when he was a graduate student in the Cinema Studies program at New York University. It also contains paperwork and course materials from courses he taught at several colleges, papers from his time as the Director of the Movie Museum in Massachusetts, as well as several obituaries for McNiven.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Roger McNiven Papers were transferred to the New York University Archives from the George Amberg Memorial Film Study Center in 2006.
Film criticism.; Tisch School of the Arts
- Series I: Coursework (RESTRICTED)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
  - Philosophy Coursework, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Course Papers, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Film Course Papers, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New York University Completed Exams, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York Univeristy Cinema Program Orientation, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Academic Transcripts, circa 1980's (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation Seminar Materials, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series II: Professional Activities
  - Thousand Eyes Theatre Schedules, Programs, and Notes, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CineClub New York City, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Spoleto Film Festival, 1979, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Conference Materials, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Reach" International Film Festival, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spoleto Film Festival Banners, 1980, circa 1980s (Box 4)
- Series III: Employment
  - Movie Museum: Nathan Mayhew Lecture Series, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Movie Museum: Box office and Financials, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Movie Museum: Schedules and Publicity, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Teaching Assistant "Film Now", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations for McNiven, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cirriculum Vitae, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Saint Francis Professorship, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Teaching Assistant "Film Criticism", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Iona Professorship, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Context of Our Gay Youth" Concordia University Professorship, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Violence in Hollywood 1954-1963" New York University Professorship, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Obituaries
  - Obituaries, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)